PROFESSOR: This brings us to one
of t he most important ideas in
reinforcement learning, and that is
because you want to do the optimal
thing but you don't know what it is
yet, you have this inevitable
trade-off between exploration,
where you try things--
which may, of course, be disastrous--
and exploitation, where you do
the things which currently
appear to be good.
You meet this all the time
in your daily life.
Some new restaurant opens
and you have a choice.
You can go to your favorite place, which
you know will bring you good
rewards, or you can try this new
thing, which is probably bad.
But it may be your new
favorite restaurant.
If you try it, you may
have a bad meal.
You may get food poisoning.
But if you don't try it, you may
be missing out on your favorite
restaurant until the end of time.
And so inevitably, the outcome is
you have to try some stuff.
And that means you have
to make some mistakes.
Let's take a look at that.
So this one's manual.
This is a variance of the
grid world, where--
well, I won't tell you what it is.
You look at this and you
think how should I act?
What is this?
Well, you've been listening to this
lecture long enough that you know this
is probably some fire pits on the
side of a bridge or something.
But for all you know, this is just 12
doors, one of which has a huge prize.
So first of all, just looking at this,
you kind of have to try everything.
Now, what if we did this?
What if we went over there and
we did that a couple times?
It looks like we're going to
get plus 1 if we go there.
Now if all we did was exploit, we would
continue going left forever and
we would receive a string of plus
1's, episode after episode.
Is that the best we can do?
Well, maybe.
We could be following the optimal
policy right now.
But, in some sense, we've
got to try other stuff.
Because we're going to be playing
this game for a while.
As far as we know, we're going
to play it forever.
And so we need to explore.
So we might do things like
jump off the cliff.
That was bad.
OK.
Maybe we'll jump off again,
just to make sure we
didn't get a weird outcome.
No, it's looking pretty bad.
We might go over here.
Oh.
That one's good.
It's so good that now the other
one doesn't even look
good to the left anymore.
And so now, we go here.
Now are done?
Well, we've got a lot of
things we should try.
Now, let me point out something, which
is that you have a lot of knowledge
about the structure of this MDP, so once
you see one fire pit, you imagine
maybe there are some others.
The algorithm has no such
concept right now.
As far as we know, jumping off this
cliff will be equally good as the good
exit, but in fact, it's
equally unsuccessful.
Well, what about this pit?
We've got to try that too.
So you spend a lot of time jumping
into pits because you really just
don't know their pits
until you try it.
So you've got to make some mistakes.
You've got to explore.
But, of course, you don't want to just
be jumping in them over and over again
once you know they're bad.
So you don't want to explore
randomly or forever.
We know we've got to try things.
The simplest way to force exploration
is what's called an
epsilon greedy policy.
So let's remember that Q-Learning did
not specify how we selected actions,
it just required that they have
sufficient variety to converge to the
optimal policy and Q values.
Now we're talking about how to select
actions in a way that will enable
Q-Learning to do it's magic.
The simplest thing we could do is be
epsilon greedy, which means at every
time step, with some presumably small
probability, we just act randomly,
just to try something out.
And with, presumably, a large
probability, we act according to our
current policies best guess, which
means we often go to our favorite
place, but every now and then when
the coin comes up random, we try
something at random.
There are some problems with
taking random actions.
Let's see an agent taking random
action and see what
those problems are.
So here's the crawler.
And now you can finally see what
this epsilon control here is.
This means 80% of the time,
we take a random action.
That's a lot of exploration.
It's not, however, a lot of progress.
Now will this work?
K Q-Learning works just fine with
lots of random actions.
It just doesn't necessarily
work quickly.
So I skip some steps.
And we've got some vague clue.
I'm going to skip a million steps.
So we compute and we compute and
we compute and we compute.
And now it actually turns out that this
bot has had a lot of experience
this year, even though
I fast forwarded it.
Presumably it should have
learned something.
Why is it not making any progress?
Well, we're forcing it to act
randomly 80% of the time.
If whenever you walked, your left leg,
80% of the time, flew out at some
random angle, you wouldn't
make fast progress.
So what happens if I
turn epsilon down.
Turn it off, and just let it go.
Be optimal.
It's not so bad.
So Q-Learning learned the right thing,
but the exploration was preventing you
from doing it.
So there were a couple issues there.
Let's see what they were.
One issue is you do eventually explore
the space, you eventually learn the
right thing, but you still keep
thrashing around if you
keep epsilon high.
So at a bare minimum, you would
eventually have to stop exploring so
much random.
Eventually, you would have to stop doing
so much exploration and allow
yourself to exploit this optimal
policy you've learned.
Another problem with epsilon greedy is
that the exploration is unstructured.
You try random things whether you need
to or not, even if you know what the
actions do.
If you know what all the actions
do, you shouldn't necessarily
be exploring anymore.
So one solution here is we just lower
epsilon over time and let the
randomness decrease.
But there are better ways, and there
are a lot of better ways.
I'm going to sketch one simple
one, which is what's called
an exploration function.
So why should we explore?
Well, random actions explore a fixed
amount, and they kind of explore
uniformly everywhere.
Every state has an equal chance of
doing an exploration action.
Here's a better idea.
Why don't we think about our actions,
and thereby our Q values, as being
something we're trying to learn?
Now, sometimes we know what they are,
and when we know what they are, we
don't have to try them anymore.
You get food poisoning a couple
times and you just stop.
On the other, when we don't know
something and our uncertainty is high,
it should be a pretty high priority
to figure that out right now.
So when the restaurant opens, you try
it, because your uncertainty is high.
Once you've tried it a couple
times, now you know.
So how can we encode this?
We'd like something that forces us to
explore areas whose badness is not yet
established, but eventually stopped.
And the basic idea here is is the quote
you often hear is, in the face
of uncertainty, you should
have optimism.
So fly into those unknown caves
and see what's in there.
Optimism shouldn't last forever, so we
might have a function like this.
Here's a very crude way of doing it.
But this basically accomplishes the goal
I sketched, which is rather than
looking at just utilities of Q states
or states, we have a function which
considers our guess at the utility,
u, and the number of
times we've been there.
And from a Q state, the number of
times we've been there means the
number of times we've tried
that action out.
So we take the utility and we add to it
a bonus that decrease as we visit
the state more times, n.
So the regular Q update
looks like this.
It says take your current estimate
of Qsa for the action, a, you
just tried from s.
This arrow means blend in this new value
on the right- hand side with
weight alpha.
So this says take our estimate and
replace it with a one-step look ahead.
And it's a sample of the instantaneous
reward we got plus our current best
estimate of the future value in
the landing state, s prime.
With an exploration function,
we can modify this.
We can modify this by replacing the Q
value with a boosted Q value, which is
artificially inflated if we haven't
tried that Q state many times, meaning
we're uncertain.
And what this does is kind of cool.
Not only does this tell you that a Q
state you haven't tried has higher
value, but also it will propagate
this bonus back.
So you don't just try things that are
unknown, you try things that are known
to lead to states that are unknown.
And that's great.
Let's see it in action.
So here is that same bot.
It's still doing a tiny bit of
exploration through randomness, but
it's implementing an exploration
function.
So this bot is implementing
an exploration function.
And as time goes on, the exploration
function will
contribute less and less.
And what that means is that even though
at the beginning it's trying
all kinds of stuff, very quickly it
figures out that it actually knows
what those actions do.
And the dominant behavior is
now one of exploitation.
And it's a slightly weird
policy, but he's off.
So unlike the other one, which had to
run millions of steps and then I had
to turn its exploration off, this one
is already moving after a very small
number of iterations.
Regret is another one of those terms
that you use all the time in daily
life, but it means something specific
here in this course.
The basic idea of regret is even though
you learn the optimal policy
eventually, because your transitions
and rewards are initially unknown,
it's inevitable that you will make
some mistakes along the way.
So you don't get to be the wise, optimal
robot without making some
mistakes in your youth.
So, for example, here, this robot.
It's wise, it's optimal, and it's
remembering back to its youth where it
jumped into that fire pit.
Now, it knows now not to do that.
And you can think of this as regret.
But a certain amount of fire pit jumping
is inevitable, because you
just had no way of knowing whether
or not it was a fire pit
until you tried it.
So what is regret formally
in this class?
Formally, regret is a measure
of your total mistakes.
It's the difference between you rewards
that you got, fire pit testing
and all, compared to the optimal rewards
you would have gotten had you
had the optimal policy all along.
Now, of course, all those rewards have
to be expected rewards, because you've
got to average all the stuff over
all the possible outcomes.
But there's this idea that there's a
total volume of mistakes you made
compared to having the optimal policy.
We'd like to minimize that.
So we've already seen Q-Learning subject
to some mild conditions.
We'll eventually learn
the optimal policy.
You're going to be optimal in the end.
So really, in practice, the game
is minimizing your regret.
Get to that optimal policy while
making as few suboptimal, in
retrospect, actions as possible.
Minimizing regret is more than
learning to be optimal.
It's more like optimally
And one example of this is random
exploration, like epsilon greedy,
compared to an exploration function.
You'll be optimal in the end with
Q-Learning either way, but you'll have
higher regret with random exploration,
because with random explanation, you
kind of keep making mistakes and
your mistakes are unguided.
You make them even when you know
yo u shouldn't do them.
So that's regret.